Hello and welcome to the lecture where we explore
microprocessors by learning machine language and
assembly language and re-implementing software
in the lowest possible language. So we're going
to start with our two instruction CPU from the
previous section and look kind of what it did
and what it didn't do. Uh because our next CPU is
going to have more data, we're going to have to
learn hexadecimal notation instead of base 2. And
then we're going to take a look at the foundations
of programming from Python for everybody. Uh
sequential, conditional, and iteration-based
programming. And we're going to re-implement all
those things in machine language and and assembly
language. We'll take a look at real CPUs that are
in the in the market now like Intel x86 and ARM.
And then the historical CPU, the the 6502. Um,
the CPU that we're going to simulate and build
is called the CD I called it the CDC 6504. It
really is mostly a 6502. Um, with some homage to
the first machine language that I ever knew, which
was the CDC 6500. So, we're going to learn about
the architecture registers, those kinds of things.
And then machine language, the actual zeros and
ones that the 6502 executes. And then assembly
language, it's is a very low-level uh language
which has a one-to-one correspondence with machine
language. And after we've played with an emulator
long enough, we'll realize that, you know,
emulators can be a pretty cool thing. And they're
actually not that hard to not that hard to write.
And we'll look at some of the emulators like
WASM and JavaScript. We're going to take a look
at how Internet Archive uh keeps old games alive
using a series of emulators that run all inside
your browser. And then we're going to finish up
talking about CPU evolution over the decades. So
if we take a look at the end of the lecture in
the previous section, we had built a CPU that had
in effect one 4-bit register, one 4-bit adder, a
clock, and then one instruction that chose between
whether or not we reset the register, the latch,
or we incremented the latch. And interestingly,
that's where we're going to start. But like what
is missing? And and the answer is if we go all
the way back to chapter 1, slide 19, Python for
everybody, a class that I started teaching in
the mid 2000s. Basically, what we're missing is
instructions that are coming from the main memory
to program the central processing unit. And those
instructions guide the central processing unit
as to how to use the hardware inside that central
processing unit. And those instructions
are zeros and ones that are represented
by electrical impulses that are coming into the
central processor. If we look at a little more
detail in the central processor, there's a number
of different resources in the central processor.
There is the ALU the arithmetic and logic unit
which has adders comparison multipliers sometimes
and then there is a place we store super fast
data to feed to and from the ALU the registers
so usually the ALU doesn't operate on things that
are in the memory we load data into the registers
and then we do computations with the ALU the PC
or program counter is the most important register
of all because it tells tells the CPU where in the
memory to retrieve the next instruction. So based
on where the PC is pointing, the CPU retrieves a
me an instruction from the memory and the register
CIR current instruction register which is not
shown on a lot of architecture diagrams but in
a sense the the machine code the 8, 16 or more
bits is loaded into the CPU in a register and
then it does what's called decoding and that is
it looks at the bits says if this an add is this
a subtract is this an increment is this a clear
what is the instruction uction and then what the
decoder does is it in effect sends signals to
the rest of the parts of the central processing
unit to take say oh okay we're going to add so
take this register feed it to the ALU add this
other register and then take the result from that
addition and put it into a different register and
of course there's a clock and the clock causes the
logic to happen our emulator is going to run on
a one hertz clock which is one one instruction
per second and um the real 6502 is 1 megahertz
which is a million instructions per second which
of course compared to modern processors is not
very many. So the machine language instructions
that we're going to do are going to be 8 bits and
there is an assembly language which is a symbolic
representation like if we want to clear the X
register set it to zero then we have an op code of
1 1 0 0 1 0 and so you can just see these op codes
for various things. There's a clear we're showing
an increment a load constant a load from memory
and then a store back to memory. We're going to
see lots of these. So, so don't don't slow down
uh and learn this. Um and so up next, we're
going to learn hexadecimal because the more
data we have, the we can't just use base 2 for
everything because it's not a very dense format.
[Music] [Applause] [Music]
So let's learn base 16 otherwise known as
hexadecimal. So the key to it would be nice
if we could just use base 2 for everything but
zeros and ones are easy to understand but when
numbers get larger like characters for example
are eight bits it's really hard to represent that
all in base 2. So it's we we tend to see in the
real world that most machine language and other
things require you to understand hexadecimal. So,
if you take a look at base two, it was easy. We
had a simple conversion table. And I hope by now
some of you have memorized this little table. I
know I've memorized I I just, you know, when
I see seven, I see three ones. When I see six,
I see 1 1 zero. I know this by heart. Okay, now
that's cool. We're seeing all numbers that we're
familiar with. Base 16 says we are going to
represent 0 through 15 with a single digit.
Right? So 15 is 15 but with two digits. And
so the whole idea of changing bases is that we
have digits. So we need to come up with a single
digit that represents 9 10 11 12 13 14 and 15.
And so I basically said, okay, wouldn't it be cool
if we would use emojis for that? Because I have
trouble remembering hexadecimal. So if we imagine
that um 10, which is kind of zero, 11, 12, 13,
I don't they don't have an emoji for four fingers,
and then 15. So I I put a shamrock in for 14. Um,
and so, so the point here is you need a
single character to represent it. And so,
so I I made this up and then I'm like, "Hey,
AI, what emojis would you use to represent
um 10 through 15?" So, there is an actual emoji
that's 10, but there is no emoji for 11. And so,
they use the pause emoji. And then they used a
clock, 12:00, 1:00, 2:00, and 3:00. And it's not
too bad. And um American Sign Languages uses one
hand. I think I think this is 11 or maybe Yeah,
I think this is 11. Uh and so British Sign
Language is different. Uh the problem is is we
don't get emotion uh when we uh make emojis. So
we can't really use American Sign Language even
though American Sign Language has way to represent
11 12 13 and 14 and 15 uh with kind of a gesture.
So the problem was is basically whatever 1930 1940
when we started using hexadecimal we didn't have
emojis it was just too early and so all we had
was ASCII characters and so we have repurposed
A through F to represent 10 through 15 for base 16
numbers. So a is 10. The first number that is not
a single digit, right? And f is 15 and f is all
ones. Four four ones is one one one is f. Okay. So
we just used a through f. It it's a little weird
because there's the letter a and then there is
the hexadecimal digit a but you have to kind of
get used to it to say oh we're in a context of a
number here. So so that means 10. A means 10. So
if we look at the conversion between base 16 and
base 10 and I got my little cheat sheet here of 10
through 15 because 0 through nine is pretty easy.
Again base 10 says that each column is a power
of 10. So the far right column is 10 to the 0ero
which is the ones column. The the middle column is
10 to the 1 which is the 10's column. And then the
third column is 10 squared which is the hundred's
column. And so 123 is 1 * 100 2 * 10 + 3 * 1 which
is 123 b 10 which of course it is in base 16. Now
we have more digits to work with. So we have 7b
base 16. Well the far right is 16 to the 0 or
1 and then the second digit is 16 to the first
power. So the result is 7 * 16 + 11 * 1 which is
112 + 11 which is 123. Now one thing we like about
base 16 is it's easily converted to and from base
2. Um and so if you have 8 bit numbers you can
represent them with two base 16 digits. And that's
what we're going to work with a lot going forward
is eight bit numbers. So you can take and convert
like 7B b 16 which is a bite and you can convert
the seven and then you convert the b and that's
the base 2. And so to some degree hexadimal is
just a more succinct base 2 where four digits of
base 2 become one digit of base 16. If we did this
on base 10, there wouldn't be this nice lineup
because you can make really long hexadesimal
numbers and they still line up on every four-bit
boundary with base 2. So for now, keep it simple.
I tend to have to go through base 10. Um, you
know, we have a eights column now. So the top line
is 1 8 + 1 2 which is 10. 8 + 2 is 10. And that is
a base 16. uh 8 which is 1 0 0 0 is 8 base 10 and
8 base 16. So all the numbers 0 through nine are
easy. And then all ones 1 one1 is 8 + 4 + 2 + 1
which is 15. And that's f in base 16. So I've
told you that I'm pretty much a whiz at base 8,
which is three base 2 digits. I I can kind of do
that in my sleep. I am not very good at base 16.
Hopefully, you'll be better at it. Or maybe not.
So, this is my this is how I do base 16 in my head
and it's not pretty. So, F is easy because that's
15. That's the largest base 16 digit. And it's all
ones, right? That's cool. It's base 16. F is one
less. It's all ones. If you add one to it, it's
it turns into the 16 column. So an E I can do E
because I just take the all the digits and I take
off the one bit, right? So that's like 14. I can
get that. A is easy because it's like nine. What's
after nine? Oh, it's A. And so I can do that. So I
understand that's 10. And B is 11. And I was like,
uh, it's kind of like one beyond uh, A. And so I
can see what B is. I have problems with C and D,
right? I mean, I eventually have to slow down and
use my brain and go A 10, B1, C12, and then I have
to convert to base 2, which is 11 1, and then
I'm like, oh, that's A+ 4. Oh, yeah, 12. Yeah,
there you go. And D just makes me crazy, right?
I sooner or later sometimes with D, I'm like,
uh, what is it? And then I have to write it
down. So um for a good time you can go ahead
and ask AI what is a good way to do hex to base
2 conversions in your head. I did that and it
was really complex. So no so maybe I'm okay by
being confused about this. So just make yourself
a little cheat sheet whenever you have to do
hex or just get used to it or look at a table.
A lot of what we're going to do is represent
characters. And characters are asking characters
are eight bits and can really nicely and densely
be represented by two hex digits. We called these
half bytes, nibbles. Um not that it matters
much, but this asky chart shows the decimal,
the hex um octal, which we tend not to use,
and then the binary. So if you look at 42,
it's kind of small on this screen, but you see
that it's 42 decimal and 0x2A hexadimal, which is
asterisk. And so I tend to just look these things
up and I don't really convert them um and just
use hex as a way to look things up in things like
ASI tables. Now while we're speaking about ASI so
so ASI is a historical code set basically that is
very western and really goes back to Latin really
and because we have 8bit bytes um and the west
built computers early on we tended to have asy
character sets were universal across computers
but that's not real there's Asian character sets
sets and Indian character sets and Arabic and
Persian character sets. They're they're all kind
of different. And so what happened was in in the
time where computing became a worldwide activity,
we needed to come up with a way to interchange
characters that are way bigger than eight bits.
And somebody came up with the idea of Unicode. And
Unicode has all kinds of character sets, you know,
Latin and ASKI start and then they just have all
kinds of character sets. Some of these are Latin
characters with like umlouts and all things like
that. And some of them are like Asian characters
that are pictograms. Now, recently emojis are in
Unicode as well. And so some of the emojis that
I've showed you are actually have a Unicode
code. Unicode represents things by 32 bits.
That's pretty large given that 8 bits is how ASI
is represented in Undeode is 32 bits. But the idea
is is there's a lot of characters sets around this
universe. Now, we're not inventing too many more
and they did things like added emojis to Unicode,
but basically 32 bits is like in the billions of
possible characters. So, I think we're probably
okay. The problem is is as we move between
computers or store data on hard drives, we don't
really want every character to take up 32 bits.
So for example, Python 3 internally represents
strings as Unicode, which means they're pretty
large. Okay? But then before we stick them on
a hard drive or send them across a network,
we condense them. And there are ways to compress
these 32-bit unic codes into shorter. So one is
UTF-32 which is four byte stuff. That's the long
one. It's fixed length and it just says we'll
take that whole unic code and send it along.
UTF-16 is fixed length. It's two bytes. It's a
lot denser and um there's a mapping. Um but the
most successful one of these is a thing called
UTF8 which might not be intuitive but basically
UTF8 is one to four bytes and it is for most ASI
UTF8 and ASI are the same things and then there's
these little extension codes I mean this is a 16-
bit code or a 32-bit code and so you can represent
all of Unicode with UTF8 sometimes you're sending
one bite if it's ASKY, sometimes two, three,
and even four bytes are being sent across. And
so UTF8 is pretty much the practice for encoding
data to be exchanged across systems. So I got to
have a graph here that sort of shows that, you
know, in 2008 there was choices to be made. Um,
but since then everything is pretty much UTF8. And
so we're at the point now where systems that are
reading and writing data to disk or the network
only pretty much use UTF8. And it happens to be
ASKY. That works. Okay. But what we're doing
is we're working on a computer from the 1970s,
which is this 6502 computer. And so we're going
to just accept that it's ASI for now. But real
computers tend to work in UTF8 and can convert
from ASI or Unicode to UTF8 uh quite nicely.
[Music] [Applause] [Music]
So in this section we're going to talk about
like what is programming and we're going to do
so by reviewing things like Python and C. And
the reason we take a look at this is that when
we write Python or C that code has to execute
eventually in machine language. So in the end
any program that we can write must also be
representable in machine language. So if we
look at patterns in high level programming, we
need to be able to replicate those patterns in
machine language. So I'm going to take you back in
time to 2008 when I first was teaching the course
that would become Python for Everybody on campus
at the University of Michigan. This was chapter 1,
slide 19. So this is for people who'd never seen
a computer, never I mean never you programmed a
computer, never didn't know what programming was.
And I introduced computer architecture in slide
19. And why was that? Well, my goal at that point
was to teach people that to become a programmer,
you kind of move into the machine. Your code
moves into the machine and it provides the
instructions to the central processing unit.
And so your goal to becoming a programmer is
to be able to provide those instructions so
you can have the overall machine do the thing
that you want to do. Now the key is those
instructions and I said this in chapter 1
slide 19 those instructions are zeros and
ones and they are what is called machine
language and those instructions are moved from
the main memory to the central processing unit.
using wires. And that was like the first half hour
of the first day of programming. And now some of
you have been with me for some time. And now we're
at the point where we're going to understand what
exactly a central processing unit is. Okay. So
let me show you some of the artifacts that I used
when teaching that class. So let's start with the
central processor. I've shown you this AMD central
processor before. We now know how to build this
chip. We understand that instructions will come
into these wires, right? So like if there is uh
eight of them, we can represent those eight wires
as a hexadecimal digit because we just learned
how to do hexadecimal. Now the place that these
instructions come from in that same picture is
the memory. And so again, you've got wires and
four of these wires equals one hexadecimal digit,
right? Lots of wires. We got chips that store,
but we've also learned how to build uh latches
that are ways to store memory electronically
and then retrieve that memory. But then we have
to come up with a way to connect these things
together. And that's what's called a motherboard,
right? And so the CPU plugs in to the Oops,
here we go. CPU plugs into the CPU slot. The
memory plugs into a memory slot. And there are
wires on this motherboard that are laid out to
pull so that the CPU can ask the memory for some
data instructions. And it comes here and it and we
also load and store the, you know, the the things
we're going to compute from the memory as well.
And so if you look at this, it's got like big and
small wires. It's mostly wires with these little
through holes that are soldered into the wires.
Um you can see kind of big things. They're like
roads and lakes, but these wires go. And so again,
I'm going to sorry, I'm going to get all stuck
on this. Four of these little pins, I mean,
eight of these little pins are two hex digits. So
we can represent all these pins perhaps with a big
long hex string. And that's kind of why we're so
obsessed with hexadecimal. I'm clearly obsessed
with hexadecimal. And the other thing that I
showed students in the very beginning was this
disc drive. Now, modern computers don't have disc
drives that actually have any physical spinning.
But basically, this was magnetic material and
this head would go in and out. I think this is now
broken, but the head would go in and out and the
data would be stored on cylinders up and down. And
so this head would move in and out. And if you're
old enough, you would remember your computer while
you're reading disc, it would go uh uh uh grunt
grunt grunt grunt grunt. Well, that grunt is this
stuff moving back and forth. And it seems as
though I have had this over 10 years and I've
scratched it and I've broken it. But you get the
idea that this was long-term storage and you could
store a lot more data than you can in RAM. The
the the memory is fast and efficient but limited
and disc drives are much larger in terms of the
amount of data they can store. And once stored,
it stays there and doesn't require power. Now,
the other thing that I showed my students,
the other thing that I showed my students is
something a little bit more modern, which is a
little more like what's in your cell phone, etc.
And this is a Raspberry Pi. And what's happened
is as they can manufacture more and more stuff
on a single chip, you can get to what's called a
single chip computer. So, in this has got the CPU,
it's got some long-term storage, it's got the RAM,
etc., etc. And so, this is got everything
in it because it's really just electronic
stuff. And as the manufacturing capability got
better and better, this is an ARM processor,
which we'll talk about later, and some RAM, etc.
And this is one of the early Raspberry Pies.
So 15 years ago, it was a little easier to show
computer architecture by showing the components
that made up computer architecture. It's not
just a picture. It was physical devices that
implemented the computer architecture. The
instructions were stored in the memory. The
whole program when the computer was off was
stored on the hard drive, loaded into memory,
etc. And the motherboard connected all of these
pieces together. So the next thing that I describe
to my students in SI502 Python for everybody
is how we construct programs and these are the
essential things like a recipe or an installation
instructions. A program is a sequence of steps to
be done in order like the Macarena. Some steps
are conditional. They may be skipped and another
way you have a group of steps that may want to be
repeated. And the fourth way is like functions. we
store and retrieve a set of steps. We are going to
cover the first three of these in machine language
to sort of prove to you that machine language can
do exactly what high level languages do just with
a different syntax and a different level of detail
that you you're limited with what you can do in
machine language. Some people feel like machine
language limitations is kind of wonderful until
you start writing really complex programs. Okay,
but the first view of machine language that you're
going like, "Wow, this is kind of nice. Maybe
I should have learned this at the beginning."
So now into some Python, we have first sequential
steps. You just write lines of code one after the
other. And like x= 2, print x, that prints out
the two, x= x + 2, we just added to two to x,
and then print x. So what next? What next? the CPU
through its program counter is advancing through
the instructions and doing whatever it is until
it executes a halt instruction which means okay
we're now done you the programmer have said we're
done there's also conditional steps like you know
x= 5 if x is less than 10 print smaller if x
is greater than 20 print bigger or print Finis
and so this is things like the print smaller is
going to run but the print bigger is not going to
run and we represent these on the left hand side
with a flowchart. And so I have been teaching with
flowcharts. A lot of people think flowcharts are
uncool, but in the next couple of lectures you're
going to appreciate flowcharts because in a sense
we are guiding the what next bit to either do
something or skip something. And so logically
they're beautiful. The the code in Python is
beautiful. There are these blocks. they either
run or don't run. But really what we're doing
at a lower level is we're manipulating where the
computer is picking its next instruction from.
And this all will come together in a little
bit. And it gets even more complex when we do
repeated steps, right? Where we have an iteration
variable, we have a loop. So n equals 5. Well,
n greater than zero. That's a top- tested loop
with a question mark. And if n is still greater
than zero, we run the body of the loop, print
it, and then subtract one from it. And now then
we know that we go back up to the top of the
loop. And the first thing we do at the top of
the loop is test it again. Is n as changed. Is
n still greater than zero? I mean, if it's not
greater than zero, we skip and finish and print
blast off. And if it is still greater than zero,
we run the iteration again and again. You of
course can create infinite loops with this
if you don't change the iteration variable
each time through the loop. And that brings
us to variables. So a variable is a place in
memory where a programmer can store data and
then later retrieve it using a variable name
like x= 12.2 y= 14 and then x= 100 replaces it.
Now, for some of you who've took my Django course,
I finally admit that X is not just a drawer that's
got a label on it. X is a pointer to an object.
So, X= 12.2 means 12.2 is an object and X refers
to that object. When we say X= 100, there's
another object called 100 and X has changed to
point to that. So if you've taken my CC class
then you realize that with pointers that this
is exactly true. A a variable is a place where
you can put one and exactly one value and when
you reassign it that value is replaced just like
this picture up next. We're going to learn about
how variables work in machine language. And it
will probably come as no surprise to you that
they work exactly like how C thinks about them
because C is one of the lowest level programming
languages which is just a tiny step above machine
language. And so instead of being Python with all
its object orientation eventually that whole
Python object orientation turns into machine
language but variables don't exactly work like
this slide tells us. But in machine language,
this slide is exactly correct. So let's
get to that now. [Music] [Applause] [Music]
Hello and welcome to our lecture on the
CDC 6504 architecture. So as you'll soon
see this is a blend of two names so that I can
avoid confusion with the actual processor that
you're simulating. So the processor that we're
simulating is the MOSS technology 6502. It is
there are many microprocessors that have deep
historical significance. The 6502 is a very
significant processor in terms of the history
of CPU architecture and its evolution. It was
launched in 1975 and the key to it was low
cost of manufacturer. It was simple. It only
had 4,000 transistors. Remember the Intel 4004
had 2,300 transistors. This ran into megahertz
and they kept the price low at $25. So it it just
allowed a whole series of hobbyist computers like
the Apple 1, that was a hobbyist computer. And
so it sort of just opened up a whole bunch of
things. And and so the problem is is that
if I named my emulator the 6502 emulator,
it would get lost in all of the confusion. So I
changed it to the CDC 6504 to pay homage to the
first computer that I ever used in the 1970s. from
Control Data Corporation. It I learned FORTRAN on
it. I learned assembly language on it. I learned
machine language on it. And I have a picture here
of a running version of this computer at the
Living Computer Museum in Seattle, Washington
that sadly is now closed after Paul Allen passed
away. But I have a video that I will share with
you. Um that is a video of a running CDC 6500
from a couple of years ago. I further was lucky
to meet an important influence in the CDC6500
history, Nicholas Wirth. He invented Pascal. I
used Pascal. I I supported the Pascal compiler.
It was a really important part of my own sort of
education was to build compilers. And so I'm going
to show you an artifact from that time period. So,
this is from I don't know if you can see it. Let's
see if you can see it here. This is from Yeah,
there you go. 1980. This was a one-year project in
computer science where I This is This is assembly
language from the CD6500. This is a compiler and
an optimizer. And so, it was written in FORTRAN,
right? These are line printers. Uh let's see if
I can find something interesting to show you.
um you know with all kinds of documentation and
so we wrote all this stuff uh in 1979 and 1980 it
was a two student project and I have kept it for
all this time right there we go okay so that's an
artifact from the CDC 6500 and again I named a CDC
6504 just so I had something to search on. So this
is the architecture of the CDC 6504 and the first
thing you have to understand is the registers and
when you start using this interactively online
you'll be reading these registers. So the most
important register the what next register is the
program counter also known as the PC as we've seen
in some earlier lectures there's the current
instruction register which is important and it
often is not shown on architecture diagrams even
though how it's very important the accumulator.
So the CDC6504 and the 6502 is an accumulator
based system and that's sort of like they have
one single most powerful register and that is
the accumulator. As you do operations, they set
flags after every operation so that you can do if
tests. So was the last result zero? Was the last
result negative? It has two more registers that
are a little less powerful than the accumulator
called the X and Y registers. And on the emulator
itself that I've built, it shows the instructions
in base 2, which makes it easier to decode. And
the data memory will be shown in hex given that
most of the time we're just going to be putting
characters into the data memory. So we program
the CDC 6504 in machine language. And so there's
some really good documentation uh that is that I
built with the help of AI. So this is a language
for the clear instruction, clear x, increment x,
etc., etc. So we'll we'll cover these in much
more detail. So let's start right away with
our first program. So you can kind of go back.
So our program is going to compute 1 + 1 = 2 in
the x register. So the PC tells the system where
to retrieve the next instruction from. So when
the program when the computer starts before we
start it running, the PC starts at zero. And so
the first instruction is 1 1 1 0 0 1 0 which is
clearing the X register. Now the system starts
with zeros in there, but it's probably smart
just to clear it anywhere anyway. Then it has an
two increment instructions and then it has an all
zeros instruction which says stop. Okay, so let's
walk this through. So when the first execution
of the first instruction is done, well that sets
the X register to zero. But then then the side
effect of that is to increment the PC register
to one and then run that instruction. And so when
that instruction runs, we increment X. And so you
can see that X is now incremented to one. But then
once that's instruction is run then it moves to
the O2 instruction and that is also an increment
which it reads and then it increments X to two
and then it runs to the last instruction which is
a break and then that stops our program. So it's
uh it runs runs three instructions and then stops.
So, at this point, you might say to yourself, "Oh,
wait a second. This seems familiar." Clearing
a register and incrementing a register and then
stopping. That's something we've done before.
Literally, in previous lectures, you have built a
two instruction computer with a latch and an adder
and a clock. And so, you can say, "Oh, well, what
is this?" Well, the register is like the latch.
The the adder is the thing that does the increment
for us because the latch's output goes into the
adder and we've hard-coded a one to the other
input of the adder. And then we have a clock that
decides when things are going to run. And then we
have an instruction which is either zero or one.
This is a this is a one-bit computer, right?
And the thing that I complained about several
times in previous lectures is that it's not
reading instructions from memory. What we just got
done doing is reading instructions from memory.
And then there's the decode logic which is always
a difficult thing for students to understand where
it is looking at literally the bits of the
instruction and using and gates and or gates
actually enabling or disabling parts of the of the
processor. So, so the the increment instruction or
the the the loading into the latch based on the
clock is turned off based on the instruction. So,
the decoding and if you look at the decoding of a
typical typical microprocessor, it's like a whole
city block, right? And so the instructions in a
real computer sitting in memory, the decoding has
to look at all eight of those bits in our 6502 and
it has to send all those bits to various places to
turn on and off elements of the registers and
elements of the arithmetic logic unit. And so
we had it this is 8bit instructions which means
we have a whole bunch of things that we can do
and control. Now, if you think about it, at this
point, if you had enough time, you could build a
CDC 6504 and manufacturing capability because if
you go to that simple CPU and that simple CPU,
the latch, the adder, and the clock can be mapped
to transistors because underneath them they're
transistors. and we covered that. And then we
showed you how to make VLSI logic design where you
can lay out in a two-dimensional grid of different
materials that cause transistors, right? And then
all you would need is a billion-dollar personal
manufacturing facility to turn those transistor
layouts into chips. and then you could cut those
chips up and then you could manufacture a 6502.
Now the goal of this course is not for you to
go and build a $2 billion uh microprocessor
fabrication facility but to understand that really
you know the essence of the entire process to
build a complex CPU and produce it. It's possible
and you understand the basics of it. So up next,
we're just going to start going into more
detail of the entire machine language.
So now we're going to do a bit of a deep dive into
the machine language of our CDC 6504 emulator. I
would suggest that if you're doing extensive work
or or even if you have some uh visual limitations
that you look at the online documentation.
It's complete and it's simple and to some
degree this lecture is really derived from the
online documentation of the CDC 6504. And so we
always are going to start and talk about the
register and just review it. Hopefully after
a couple of lectures it'll be sort of natural
to you. The program counter is the what next
instruction memory starts at zero. The accumulator
is the the best register. So it it's an the CDC
6504 is an accumulator based computer which means
that you can do more things with the accumulator
than other registers. There are flags the Z and
the N. And there's actually more in the 6502,
but Z in the N is all I've put in here. Z says,
when you're fiddling with registers, was the last
result zero or was the last result negative? And
these are used to control ifs and jumps and loops,
the Z and the N. The X and the Y are index
registers. They're just a little less capable
of the accumulator register, and they're actually
used in uh index loads, as we'll see. Instruction
memory is shown in base 2 for easy decoding.
Now the data memory I show that in hex because
mostly what we're putting in the data memory is
strings and asky characters. Okay. So the index
instructions are good for loops. And the x and y
registers are often used to control counted loops
or actually look things up within an array. And
so we have a an op code to clear the X register,
clear the Y register, add one to it, add one to
X and Y, and then subtract one from X and Y. Now,
if you think about it, the the CPU that we built
clears and increments with two instructions. So
we had an instruction of one which increments
and zero which clears. So in addition to 8bit
instructions, there are 16- bit instructions. And
so in 16- bit instructions, there is usually a
numeric value or a constant or an address that
is in the immediately following. So that means
that the program counter in this case goes up
by two. And so this the load a instruction can
take a constant value. So you can load a the
character asterisk which is a 42. And so you
see the load a instruction at memory location
zero and then the actual 42 value in this case
base 2 is at instruction one or you can basically
say we're going to do a load but the address that
we want to load from is taken from the following
eight bits. In this case we're going to load from
memory location two and the two is stored in
instruction memory location three. So these we
call these immediate and the reason we kind of
call these things immediate is the the the the
constant or the address is immediately following
the instruction in case and so these turn into
16- bit instructions. You could see it as you
load one instruction in and there would probably
be both a current instruction register and an
immediate register. And you would notice that this
instruction that we just loaded has an immediate
and so we'd load both of those things and then
have them in the CPU to to work. So loading and
storing operations are important. So you can
load into the A register, the X register and the
Y register. And you can store into the A register,
X register and Y register. And you can either load
a constant like set a to zero load a hashtag zero
or you can say go get memory location you know
F3 and load that in. Okay. And so those are the
instructions that do loading and storing. Now when
we start dealing with arrays we have the we can
use the X and the Y. So we can say this address is
kind of the beginning of the array and then X and
Y are the offset in the array. So you you start
seeing that you can set x to zero. You can load
something from a starting point in memory plus
x and then you can add one to zero and then load
something again from that same place in memory
plus x and then x become and y are really well
designed to use as iteration variables. And then
this is where the accumulator is important where
the accumulator is the register that can do the
most things. So we can't add arbitrary values. So
we can't add we can add one to X and Y registers
but we can't add five. So ADC hashtag five adds
five to it. So the same for subtraction. And
that you can either add an immediate value like
a constant or you can go into some memory and
grab that memory and add it to the accumulator.
So you can see it says ACC equals ACC plus memory
bracket address. That means that we're adding in
the data memory at the position that's addressed.
But the address it's an immediate instruction and
the next one is the address that we're going to
add. So adding and subtracting is the accumulator.
Now the everything that is adding, subtracting,
loading, storing, whatever it's doing to whatever
register sets the Z and the N flags. And
so it just as part of the final putting
the value into the register, it sets Z and N. So
if the value we put in to the register was zero,
the Z flag will be a one. It'll be set. If the
value we put in was 42, the Z flag will be zero.
And the same with positive and negative. Negative
numbers are numbers that have the first bit,
the tie bit one. We we're not doing too much,
we won't be doing too much with negative in
this class. will mostly be setting the zero
but you can do like less than or equal with
the negative. So combinations of uh Z and N can do
greater than or equal, less than or equal, etc.,
etc. And so there is a uh special instruction
called the compare instruction that says, hey,
let's check to see if the accumulator equals five.
But you're really saying five accumulator check
them. It's kind of like a subtraction without
actually doing the subtraction. And then set
subtract set the Z and N flags from the result of
the subtraction and then throw away the result of
the subtraction. So that's what the comparison
operators are. Okay? And so you can compare
um the accumulator, the X, and the Y. So there's
no if statement in machine code. All there are are
conditional jumps. And so that you'll have to get
used to it. When I started in Forran, everything
was a go-to before we had structure ifs, if then
else. That that's not in machine code. There is a
conditional jump, which we'll talk about. And the
way you get the conditional jumps to activate is
every instruction that changes a register and the
compare instructions with don't change registers
set the result flags. There's a Z, which is was
the result zero or not? And then the N is was
the result negative or not. And so if the result
is zero, the Z is one and the N is zero because
Z is not negative. If the result is positive,
Z is zero because it's not zero and N is zero
because it's not negative. And if the result is
negative, Z is zero and one is negative. And yes,
you can use these together to create greater than,
greater than or equal to, equal, less than, less
than or equal to. So that's kind of what you're
thinking about, right? is uh how to implement what
we think of as the traditional logical operators
in a highle language. So the closest we have to an
if statement is a compare and then a conditional
jump. And so there are four instructions,
right? There's more of them, but these are
the four that matter. The BEQ branch if equal,
that means the Z flag is set. B ne branch if
not equal mean means the Z flag is clear and
then branch minus BMI and then BPL means branch
plus. So for example here's a little tiny bit of
code that we can do an uppercase. We're going
to convert a lowercase to uppercase and leave
uppercase alone. Okay. So we do hashtag quote
p quote which is the ASCII value for 'p'. Now,
normally we'd read this from input, but we're not
going to. We're just going to hard-code the the v
the value we're going to convert. Then we're going
to compare that to the ASCII value for a. So that
comparison then sets the z and the n. And then
we're going to say BMI to location 08, which we'll
talk about this in a second, how that works, how
you know that that's 08. That's kind of tricky.
But that's an address in instruction memory, the
08. And then if it's minus, we will skip the next
instruction. But if it's not minus, we're going
to subtract hex 20 because that's converting to
lower case. If you look at the ASCII table, you
see that the the difference between an uppercase
A and a lowercase A um is 20. The lowercase A is
20 hex higher than an uppercase A. And then that
BMI is 08. If it's already uppercase, meaning
it's a lower number, that jumps to the BRK and
the program stops. You can think of this as if
the accumulator is less than the letter A, we're
going to skip the next instruction. And if the
if we don't skip, we're going to subtract 20 hex.
And if we do skip, we're done. And then in the
accumulator will be the uppercase letter whether
or not the original letter that was loaded into
the accumulator was uppercase or lowercase. And
so this is where flowcharts come back. Remember I
said flowcharts are not cool. Although if you ask
AI often flowcharts are cool. They're very retro.
Well the key to flowcharts is that they work
exactly like assembly and machine language. So if
we look at the first instruction which is loading
the accumulator with the letter the lowercase P
then we're doing a compare instruction. So the
compare instruction is not something we think of
in a high level language. We're asking a question.
We're like compare the accumulator to a and set
the flags. That's what the compare instruction
is doing. Is accumulator equal to less than or
greater than a? And so then we say was the result
of that particular compare a BMI negative because
BMI means is the N flag set and if the N flag is
set we're going to jump to to instruction memory
location08. If not we're going to fall through.
And by the way, the actual dollar 08 is in the
immediately following uh instruction memory.
And so where to jump is the 08. Then if we don't
jump, we're going to subtract 20 hex. And the 20
is also in immediate memory. And then the place
the program stops is at instruction memory 0x08.
So the way if you're doing this by hand, you'd
actually kind of leave instruction memory 05
blank, lay everything else out, and then you
see where 0x08, the halt ends up, and then you
would go copy that back in to the 0x05 memory
location. That seems painful. Painful even for
eight instructions. Thankfully, we have this
thing called assembly language. So there's no
need to compute these instructions by hand. And
so if you look at the BMI in this code, you say
BMI skip and then right before the instruction
that you want to skip to, you put a little label
with a colon. So skip colon. Now, it turns out
that just like I told you on the last slide,
the assembler is making two passes. It literally
is assembling all the code and remembering where
it needs to change addresses. So it kind of keeps
track of that's going to wherever skip turns out
to be because skip could be later. So it has to do
it all. Has to lay it all out. Has to figure out
where it's going to go in the memory and then it
has to go back and replace the skip with the eight
hex so that it knows what it's doing. But for us,
we don't care. We write assembly language. We use
labels. and the whole notion that you've got to
do two passes by hand, we just write assembly
language. And so our larger example codes will be
assembly language. And so the jumps, like I said,
are far simpler than if logic. So in addition to
the BEQ, the B branch equal, branch not equal,
branch minus, and branch plus, we also have an
unconditional jump. That's ignoring, you know,
jump to an address that just says don't look at
the flags, just unconditionally jump. But just
think about this for a second. The PC, the program
counter is itself a register. So even though we
have these op codes that say branch, sure, or
jump, in a sense, you could think of these as
just a set of the PC. If the in if if we had a
assembly language that said set PC to this address
then that would mean that the PC the next time it
would retrieve an instruction would go to where
it's at. So you can think of a jump as set the PC
to this address or a jump conditional says if this
condition is true set the PC to this address and
of course these are all 16 bit instructions and
so that address is in the immediately following uh
memory uh memory location. Okay. So there are also
no for and while loops in machine language and so
we have to construct them with these comparisons
and conditional branching. So I'm not going to
bother showing you the machine language for this.
The emulator will allow you to see that. Um I'm
just going to show you the assembly. So the in
the on the left is assembly language and assembly
language is a textual language that is not zeros
and ones but there is a one-to-one correspondence
that every single assembly language statement
turns into directly into machine language. Now
it might be a 8-bit machine language or a 16-
bit machine language and the assembler which
is a program that converts this text to machine
language. The assembler knows all the rules, the
syntax of the pound sign five. So really while
we have been talking about machine language, we
mostly been talking about assembly language. So
let's take a look at a really simple for loop.
Now this for loop doesn't do anything. It's just
constructing this for loop or a while loop. It's
a top- tested loop. So if we go through this,
the first thing we do and and I mentioned that
X registers are good for loops and arrays.
First thing we're going to do is we're going to
clear the X register. Then we're going to have
a label that says here's a place we're going
to come back to. But that doesn't take up any
memory. That just is something that the assembler
is going to remember that location, wherever that
location is. Then we're going to compare the X
register to five. Like that's saying, huh, hey,
let's just look at X. Let's look at five. And
then set the Z and the N flags. And BEQ to end.
end is a label in this case. So if x equals 5,
we're going to jump to the end label. If we're
not jumping, we're coming through. We're going
to add one to x, which is the inx instruction
or x= x + one. Now in this right hand side,
these x's are not really just any old variable.
That means the x register. So there's only like
the accumulator and the X and the Y and program
counter and instruction register, but they're just
these are not variables. These are just plain old
registers. So after the INX instruction, we do
an unconditional jump and you can see that on
the flowchart on the right hand side perfectly
represented to jump back to loop. Now where is
loop? What number is loop? We don't know and
we don't care. But the assembler is going to
turn that before it gets loaded into the memory
as machine language. Loop becomes a number just
like end becomes a number. So we jump to the top
of the loop and you can see that we added one to
X and then we compare it to X. We we check the
branch which does in the second time around it
goes straight down and adds one again. So you
can see this is a for loop that's going to go
round and round and round until X is equal to five
and then it's going to jump to end and at end the
program is going to halt. In the next section
we're going to go into we're not going to worry
quite so much about the machine language. We're
going to worry more about the assembly language.
So we can talk about building simple algorithms
in machine language but writing them in assembly
language. And so if you look at the summary
of the machine language we've talked about so
far. This is not all of them but they're kind of
simple. You load, you compare, you jump, etc. And
you can branch and jump and clear and increment
and stop. And it's a real really simple thing.
And it is both simple and powerful, but it's
actually super verbose because of its simplicity.
Now it is time to start building a little more
complex machine language assembly language
applications. And as always, these slides are not
necessarily the best reference. Once you listen
to them, you should probably start looking at
the online documentation that I provide for the
CDC 6504. So we'll start with another review of
the architecture. By now, this should be pretty
familiar to you. We have a program counter which
is telling us where in the instruction memory to
retrieve the next instruction. We have the
accumulator register which is kind of the
most flexible register. We have the Z and the N
flags that tell us whether last thing we did in
a register was zero or negative or a compare
instruction. The X and the Y registers are
registers that are a little less capable than
the accumulator. We show instruction memory in
base 2 and data memory we show in hex because it
usually contains ASCII. So there is a new thing
that's only in assembly. Labels are something
that's as uh only in assembly and this data
directive is the thing that's only in assembly.
Everything we've done so far in the assembler is
populating the instruction memory by parsing the
instruction the assembly language instructions
and producing the zeros and ones that are the
machine language. But there's also this thing
called a DATA directive where we can fill the
data memory up with some preloaded data. Before
the program starts we load there's a step called
"loading". We load the program into the memory can
load the instruction memory and we can preload the
data memory with this data directive but it's not
machine code it is something that assemblers do
and give us a loadable image that includes a data
segment basically and it can either be a quoted
string or a series of hex digits and We mostly
will use quoted strings. So you can print hello
world by having a single line of machine language
break which means halt and but then have the data
filled with hello world. And it just turns out
that the emulator dumps out the data when it's all
done. So this is the simplest program. It's not
really machine language, but it's the simplest
program in the emulator to make it print hello
world. So here's just a couple. So in this one
we're going to add 27 + 15 and then store it in
memory location zero. So we load 27 an immediate
immediate constant into the accumulator. Then we
add 15 which is another immediate constant. So
that's 42. And then we're going to store that in
location memory location zero. So you can see by
the and then we halt. So by the time the program
counter makes to zero 05 hex there is a single
0x2A which is 42 and hex and then you can see that
that prints out asterisk because if you go look
at your ASCII chart asterisk is 42 decimal. Our
next example is just printing hello and so we're
going to end up putting this in memory so that
the program will dump out the memory starting at
memory location zero after the program finishes.
So, we do an immediate load of the letter H
and we store it in memory location zero. We
do an immediate load of the letter E, store
that in location one. We do immediate load of
the letter L and store that in location two. And
then we store that again in location three because
there's two L's. Then we do a immediate load
of the letter O and we store that in location
four. And then we quit. And then if you look at
the memory, there is H E L L O in the memory in
hex. And then you can see that the program prints
HELLO out when it's all done. And again, this
is just exploring some assembly language/machine
language. So now we're going to do a little more
complicated and a little more practical example.
So we are going to uppercase a whole string of
characters and we're going to take the characters
from memory, read them all from memory in a loop,
check them, convert them to uppercase, and then
store them back if necessary. So the key to this
is our data is going to be preloaded using the
data directive in memory locations 0 through 4.
And that's the lower hello with a h upper-cased
already. So now we've run it. You can see the
status is halted. And you see that it printed
out an uppercase hello. And the only real thing
that it changed was memory location 1 2 3 and 4
are now the uppercase versions of those letters.
Now before we go through that code in some
detail, let's think about uppercasing this
string in other languages. Now if you're a Python
person be like "Hello".upper. There's a method.
"Hello" the string is an object and you can call a
method upper(). Now it's not changing the Hello to
HELLO. It is just giving you a copy of that. Now
if we didn't have upper, we would have some pretty
ugly Python. So, you can't change a Python string
in place. So, you have to make a variable. In this
case, I'll call it me because it's like the
memory, but you can't change mem in Python.
You got to make a new one. So, then we're going
to have this for loop for XR, which kind of is
my way of saying X register is range len of mem.
That's going to run XR through zero through four
up to but not including uh five. And then we're
going to retrieve memory one character of memory
from XR to XR + one. Put that in the accumulator.
And if the accumulator is greater than or equal
to A and less than or equal to Z means it's
between A and Z inclusive then we're going to
compute the new character. And now you you'll see
this chr and ord. And the problem is is that in
Python we're not even using ASCII. The "Hello"
is Unicode. So ord says give me the ordinal of
the current character I'm looking at subtract the
ordinal of a lower case a and adding the ordinal
uppercase a. Now, this wouldn't necessarily work
for any set of characters because Unicode can
have a lot of things and so the actual uppercase
is a little more complex inside of Python. So,
we've computed the uppercase character if we
know it's a lowercase character by mathematics
and then we append it to the new version of the
memory building that up one string at a time and
then we print it out. And so you can't even
do this because Python is not really designed
for low-level array like things. Lists are not
arrays. Although if you took my C programming
class, you would understand that they're kind of
arrays. Okay. So let's take a look at this in C,
which is a lot more like assembly language.
So if we take a look at the top of this,
we include the stdio.h and we have a main program
and we use the register register int star ac. Now
for those of you who don't know C, the register
is a is a keyword in the C language and it says
this is going to be something that I'm going to
want to make high performance. So put it in a
register if you possibly can. Then I'm going
to create a character array named mem. Now,
this is going to be a six character array with
a zero termination. The letters "Hello" followed
by a zero. And so then what we're saying is we're
saying for xr equals zero as long as mem sub xr,
we're now looking for that zero terminated
string. As long as me xr is non zero,
continue. And then add one to xr. So then we take
our that's our index variable - our loop iteration
variable. So we say let's take the accumulator and
load in memory sub xr because xr is our sort of
index variable and in this case we're dealing with
ASCII and we know it. So if uh the accumulator
minus a is less than zero we continue and if
you recall and see the continue does mean that
the increment part of the for loop is executed
XR++. if not we're just going to say M memory sub
XR equals the accumulator minus 0x20. So we're
doing the case conversion there and putting it
right back into memory. That for loops runs five
times and then we print out the uppercase. So now
we are going to finally walk through the assembly
language version of this. So I've got the code on
the left and I've got the before memory and the
after memory on the right. Now one of the things
that you'll notice is that I have given you on
on the right hand side I've given you the sort of
pseudo code for the C code that corresponds to the
assembly language that we're going to do. So we're
going to effectively construct a for loop that's
going to loop through an array of characters. So
the first thing we do is we're going to set X to
zero with CLX and then we're going to have a label
to come back up to the top of our for loop. The
next instruction LDA $00, X is the new instruction
we haven't used so far and this is an indexed
load into the accumulator. The dollar 0 is the
starting address and the X register contains our
offset. So it basically adds X to wherever we're
at and then that becomes the address and then
we're going to load that into the accumulator.
Now, that act of loading into the accumulator
is going to set the Z flag and the N flag as any
change to any register does. And so, we're going
to use a BEQ, which is really kind of branch zero.
That means if the accumulator is zero, we're
going to follow the branch. But in this case,
the accumulator is going to have uppercase H
0x48. And so, BEQ is not going to branch. So,
we're going to fall through. And then we're
going to start our if test in a sense. Compare
the accumulator to lowercase a. Now recall that
in ASI uppercase A is less than lowercase A in
the ASCII chart. So if it's already uppercase
that comparison is going to be minus, right?
It's going to be negative and so we're going to
branch to in effect a label that I called cont,
which is sort of like a continue. We're going to
skip the subtract if it's already an uppercase.
So, BMI skips the subtraction if it's already
uppercase. Then we come into the continue label
and then we are incrementing X. Now remember that
continue actually runs the increment of a for
loop. And then we're going to jump back up to the
top of the loop, but X is now one. And now we're
going to load index load from at location zero
with X of one. And so now we get the 0x65, which
is the lowercase e. And we're going to check to
see if we're out of the loop. We're not so we're
going to fall through. We're going to compare
the lowercase e to lowercase a. And in this case,
it's not minus because e is greater than a.
And so we're going to do the subtraction. So,
we're going to convert that to uppercase by
subtracting 20 hex. And then we're going to
start right back into that location, which
is location zero indexed by the X register,
which is one. And so that's going to put 0x45 into
location 0x01. Then we drop into the continue. We
add one to X. The X register becomes two and we
jump to the top of the loop. So you see that how
this is kind of working, right? So now X is two.
And so we do an index load of of location 0 + 2
branch if it's equal to done. Check to see if it's
uppercase already. And in this case it's not. we
subtract. So at some point you can follow this. It
will go round and round until we get to an offset
of five. Jump to the top of the loop. We're going
to load location zero plus x which is five. And
in this case it's going to be a zero. And then the
BEQ is going to be true in a sense. And then we're
going to jump to done. And then the application
is going to finish and print out its after data
which is fully upper cased hello. That's a bunch
of assembly language and C and Python. And I would
say that you're going to spend a bunch of time
with the emulator and a bunch of time with the
emulator documentation. And hopefully with
some time this will all make sense to you.
Hello everybody and welcome to another
walkthrough and this time we're going to
do some walkthrough
in the CDC 6504 machine language emulator.
So let's first just talk a little bit
about all the
things that we can do here. So this is
kind of our machine language emulator. We
have a series
of instructions. It starts out all zeros.
We have data memory. We have 256
instructions. We have 256
data memories. We have an accumulator
register, an X register, and a Y register
taken from the 6502.
And then we have the program counter which
points to where we're at. Our program
counter currently
says zero pointing at instruction memory
zero. The Z is a flag that once we do a
calculation or store
some stuff, it'll and the result of that
is a zero. The Z will check and N stands
for negative.
So you can you can branch if negative,
branch if positive, branch if zero.
And so
these are
used to do a pattern of compare then
branch. Um we can load a program from
here. Let's just load
a simple sample so you can see it. Um you
can also view the assembly language. And
so what I'll tend
to do is I'll tend to put the assembly
language over here. And um and then I've
got this narrate
execution. You can hover over each of the
memory locations and it tells you for
example that this
0x0 location is a E2 and hex and it is a
clear instruction. Now sometimes this is
instruction,
sometimes it's data when we're doing load
immediates. So this it it tells you you
know if it's ASKY it'll tell you what the
ASKY character is. Um and so it has to
interpret this
but this is just zeros and ones in the
computer memory and it's contextualized
what's going on.
So this is just a clear instruction. Oops. A
clear instruction, an increment instruction,
and an increment instruction. And then a
break, which is just a zero,
which stops
the thing
from running. And we can see the same thing
right here in the assembly line. It's clear,
increment, increment, break. Eventually,
we're going to want to just look at the
assembly. It
just makes our lives a lot simpler to
watch what's going on. Um, but reality,
it's zeros and ones.
Um and so we have a couple of uh options
here. We can start the application. We can
run it a single
step. Uh and we can reset it. But that
clears everything and we got to load a new
program.
But we have this cool feature called
narrate execution. And it slows it down
and describes
everything that's going on. And so I'm
going to tell you in advance what's going
to happen. It's
going to clear the X register. And you got
to watch the X register here.
Then it's
going to
add one to the X register. Watch the X
register. and then add one again to the X
register. And when
it's all said and done, it'll stop and
nothing else will have changed except the
Cure X register
will have a two in it. So, I'm going to move
this over here and you can kind of watch as
the program counter moves along and just
kind of that assembly is there for you to
remember. Now,
later you can write assembly and get it
assembled. So, let me go ahead. It's got
narrate execution turned on and let me
start it. PC 0 PC01 increment X register
PC0X02 increment
X register PC0X03 break no printed output.
Okay, so you saw what happened there. Um,
let me go and do this a little more
slowly. Let me reload it. Load simple
sample. And I'm going
to instead when we narrate execution, I'm
going to hit step. So you saw it run
automatically. And
so I'm going to do step. So it's going to
run one instruction and narrate it when I
press step. PC0.
Okay. So notice that the Z flag now the
and it's a it's a one one bite
instruction. So the PC went up
by one. The Z flag is now set. It's not a
negative number because the X register is
a zero which is
not negative. And that is the result of that
particular instruction. So let's step again.
PC01 increment X register. So we
incremented X. So if we look at X, X has
now gone from zero to one.
The program counter is ready for the next
instruction. But because X is
now one,
neither the
Z nor the N flag is set. So let's step one
more time. PC0x2 increment X register.
Okay. So now
the PC the next register that we're going
the next instruction is going to be 0x03
and the X register
is two. The Z and the N flags are set
accordingly. When we step again, we're
going to hit this break,
which is a stop. And then the program
execution break, no printed output. And
what it's talking
about no printed output is in future ones,
we put some data. When we put data in here,
the printed output comes out of the first
few up to a zero bite in the memory. But
this one has no
particular memory. Okay. So, let's just
take a look at a couple of other things
that we have.
It has a bunch of documentation. It's
pretty cool. It's uh it's
probably more
you can read
this. AI can read this. It's pretty cool.
That's just a URL that you can go paste
into AI if you
want and you can ask AI for help writing
this code. Um we'll see how well
AI does
with this,
but it has documentation. We also need an
asky chart, right? I have this is not a
text one. So,
but we have a little asky chart that tells
the space is 32 decimal. It's 20 hex and
00 1 0 0.
And remember that that hex you can do a 4bit
to one column hex to binary conversion. And
and for me I start seeing things like I'll
look at like this one here. I know that's
a seven. So
that's 27. Um I'll see this 111. And I'll
see that as an F. So you'll start
to see
hopefully
after a while you'll kind of have a hex
tobinary conversion in your me in your
mind. decimal is a
pain in the neck. You got I just got to hand
convert both decimal to hex and binary. And
so that's pretty much all of the features
of the application. And so next we're
going to go through
uh some of these things in a little bit
more detail. Um, and so, uh, we'll come to
those in a
Hello and welcome to another computer
architecture CPU emulator walkthrough.
And so in this one we are going to go
through a number of simple samples. And
I will turn on the viewing of the assembly
language down here so we can see that. And
and so this this one here is really simple.
It is going to load a constant into the A
register
27. That's a decimal 27. And then we're
going to add 15. So this is going to be 27 +
15 and then
we're going to store it into memory location
0 0 and then we're going to stop. So this is
going to cause a little bit of output. So
let's go ahead and narrate the execution and
then start
it running. Let's put this in a place. Well,
we don't want to hide the memory because the
action
is going to happen here in the memory. So
here we go. PC0x 0. Load accumulator.
Immediate 0x1
B. PC0X02. Add with carry. Immediate 0x0F PC
0x04. Store accumulator to address 0 PC0X06.
Great printed output asterisk. So this time
we stored something in the memory. So the
the the
the program will dump the memory up to a
zero byte. like C, right? It'll dump the
memory up to a zero byte. And 0x2A, let's go
look at our ASCII chart. 0x2A 0x2A 0x2A,
there we go, is a 42 decimal. Interesting
choice of number. And it's an asterisk. And
so it's a 0x2A. You can see it in the
memory. And when the program stops, it
prints it out.
Okay. So then let's take a look at another
simple example. Let's take a look at the
assembly
language for it. So this is going to
basically stick that letter H into the into
the accumulator
then store it into lo memory location zero
and then put a I in the accumulator and
store that in
memory location one. So let's let's go ahead
and step that. PC0x 0 load accumulator
immediate 0x48.
I'll go to the next instruction which is
going to store that one.
And now we're going to load the I load
accumulator.
So 0x69 is the letter I. And now we're going
to store it. PC0x06. Store accumulator to
address
one. So this that we just put some some data
into memory location one. We're going
to step one more. It's going to stop and
it's going to print out what is here in ASI
PC08.
So it said hi. Okay. And so let's do one
more simple one. And this one's weird. So I
have a single instruction which is break
which is stop. And you'll notice it says
0000 right away. But I use the assembly
language data pseudo. We call these pseudo
ops. And it
preloads the data. And it says, and this is
hello world. So you can see it's hello world
in ASKI. 0x20 is the space. So we're just
going to run this, but it's going to
immediately stop,
but it's going to dump the memory because we
preloaded data into memory. And so this is
really showing you more about how this data
pseudo operation works. PC0X00 great printed
output. Hello world. Okay. And so let me
then show you one more thing in this. I want
to you
you can write code in the assembler. Okay.
So you this is a little text editor and is
you read the
assembly language. You go into the
documentation, read the assembly language
and then you can say
take this code and assemble it. So it
assembled it and so now it says hello CA for
E. So there's
the So in location five is the space and
then C is the 43. Let's go ahead and bring
up a ASKI
chart so we can figure out what this memory
location six is. It's a 0x43 and that's C.
And then 41 is the A. Right? So you can see
this. And now we're going to run it.
It's only got one instruction which is a
stop instruction but then it's going to
print out its
output hello. So so that was that's just
really showing you the the
data the data thing. So and we later we will
use this to preload data and
then write code that reads from memory and
does something to that memory. But for now,
I hope you found this walk through with a
couple of simple examples useful.
Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
computer architecture for everybody. In this
walkthrough, we are going to do some more
work with our CDC 6504 emulator. We're
going
to build
our first loop. So, let me go ahead and load
that loop up and then turn on the
assembler
so
we can see it. Oh, not that one. We're not
going to change it. That would
be where we
would change
it. , let's view the assembly. We just want
to be able to look at it when we're near it.
Okay.
, and so this is not going to use any
memory. So I can just leave
the view
assembly
over here. Actually can bring it all the way
over here because we're not going
to get
into
the second second half of the instruction
memory because we're done here. So let's get
a review of
what we're going to do. So this is a Python
for the X register in range five because
this is going to go this is going to be a
loop that goes 0 1 2 3 4 and then when it
hits five
it's going to jump out. It's not going to
execute the body of the loop for the value
five. As soon
as it hits five, as soon as it's equal to
five, we're going to jump out of the loop.
So the first
thing to note is this syntax of a label.
labels are not actually in the machine
language. They're
making it so that we don't have to put
numbers in this jump instruction or the
branch if
equal instruction. So, we can basically say,
"Hey, assembler, you're pretty good at
keeping track of
stuff." This loop is going to turn into an
address and we're going to jump to an
address, which is a
number, or we're going to jump to an offset.
And please calculate the offset. do all that
calculation for me so I don't have to put
numbers in here. So these aren't really
instructions,
they're pseudo instructions much the data
pseudo instruction. So let's take a look at
how these things end up in the machine
language. So let's take a look at the jump
to loop. That
jump to loop is the jump back up to the top.
And so we're sitting here at location
0x06
and
that's a jump instruction. And the the loop
is the address which is what the
program
counter is
going to get set to and that's going to set
the program counter to one which
means it's
going to
jump to instruction one and that is the
compare instruction. So the calculation of
this number
one is done by the assembler as it looks at
this loop symbol and it re keeps track of
it. Right?
So it took two to two passes. You can
calculate it backwards jumps but forward
jumps are a little bit
harder. Now the BEQ is even a little bit
trickier. Okay? Because of course the BEQ
checks the Z flag.
If the two last comparison was equal then
the result of that subtraction would be
zero. And so
and so we're going to be EEQ. So here's the
BEQ at at PC location 0x03. And
then we take
a look
at the immediate. So this immediate you
would it's going to jump to location
8 which
is the
end of the program which is a break
instruction but you look at this offset and
that's a three
011 is a three and so what this is is this
is a relative offset again computed by the
assembler on
our behalf. Now, it turns out that this
three is going to be added to the current
program counter,
but it's not added to four. It's actually
added to five. And that's because the
program counter
retrieved the BEQ instruction. Then it
retrieved the immediate instruction. And as
a side effect,
it incremented the PC. And so the PC once
this BEQ is executing is five. So 5 + 3 is
8. And you listen as you read it. It'll
it'll have computed the 5 + 3.
it'll know
that this
is five and it'll add three to it and it'll
know eight. And so when we're narrating this
execution,
you'll hear it talking about branching to
eight when 8 is not really sitting here in
the base 2. Okay. So let's go ahead and do
some steps. I'll take it slow at the
beginning
and then we'll speed it up. PC0 clear X
register. So we cleared the X register but
again it already
was zero because the program was just
starting but the PCs moved up to one. The
zero is set
because we cleared the X register. We
touched the X register. We did a
calculation
which
means we set it to zero. Okay. And that sets
the Z flag. The next instruction is going to
be compare to five. PC0x01. Compare X
register with immediate 0x0. Okay.
Now the
interesting
thing is that is not Z because it's not
equal. It does a subtraction. So it takes 0
minus five,
but it didn't store the result of that. It
just set the flags. And so that compare
instruction
doesn't change registers. It just changes
flags. So now we're at the point where Z is
not set and
N is set. And so the fix we're going to do
is we're going to run this BEQ instruction.
That means if the Z is set, we're going to
jump to end. And end is three characters,
three bytes beyond location five. But in
this first time, we're not going to jump
because the
Z flag is not set. So let's do a step.
You'll see it's going to just jump over it
to location 5 PC3
address. So you'll notice it calculated the
5 + 3 equals 8. But because the Z flag is
not set,
it just went to PC5 and didn't touch the PC.
So you can always think of a
branch or a jump as a setting of the PC
value. But in this case,
it computed a relative offset of the current
PC, which was five plus three.
And that
would have
been where we jumped. So the next thing
we're going to do after we didn't
jump is
we're going
to increment X PC increment X register. So
now X is one. It's not negative and it's not
zero.
And the next thing we're going to do is
we're going to jump back up to location
one.
So this
is an absolute jump to location one. Whereas
the branch EQ was a positive offset jump.
PC06 jump to address one. So we're back at
one. You see the PC is one. And
now the next
thing
we're doing is going to do the comparison.
PC01. Compare X register with immediate
0x05. Now one is
less than five. So we get the N flag. So
we're not going to file this branch. PC0x03
branch if equal
address 0x08 didn't branch. Now we're going
to increment PC05 increment X register.
And
now we're
going to do an absolute jump a goto. PC0x06
jump to address one. So you let's
let's go
ahead
and just run it for a while. We'll wait.
Maybe I'll try to stop it when X is three
and then
see what's going on. So let's just run it.
PC0x01. Compare X register with immediate
0x05. PC0X03
branch if equal address 0x08 PC 0x05.
Increment X register PC 0x06. Jump to
address one. PC0X01.
Compare X register with immediate 0x05. PC
0x03 branch if equal address 0x08 PC 0x05
increment X
register PC 0x06 jump to address one P Okay,
so now we are jumped to address one. I I
caught it
halfway through it. Okay, I did the compare
and it fell through still because it's not
equal. The
next time we're coming up, X is going to be
five. So, I'm going to start stepping at
this point. ,
, we're going to I think this is, , oh, no,
it's we I stopped it before the beq. Okay.
So,
so it's still negative because we checked to
see if four and if if four was less than
five and it
is. So that the the the n is still. So,
we're going to branch x03 branch equal
address 0x08.
Do one more. This is going to be the
increment. PC0x05 increment
X register. Now
we're going to do
an absolute jump back up to the top of the
loop. PC06 jump to address one. Okay, here
we are. So
look, X is now five. This is a top tested
loop. The next thing we're going
to do is
we're going
to compare it and watch the little Z flag.
Happy little Z flag turn on. One step.
PC0x01 compare X
register with immediate 0x05. There we go.
So the Z register is now set and the BEQ is
going to read
the Z the Z flag actually not register. I
think as one bit registers. Okay. And so the
BEQ is
going to jump and remember it's going to
take this three 1 and add it to five and
jump to eight. So
let's party. PC0x03 branch if equal address
0x08 and now we're at X08 and then we're
going to do PC
X08 break no printed output. So there's no
printed output because we didn't store
anything. We didn't
store anything in the memory. We are just
showing you how loops work. Okay. So I hope
this has been
helpful in a simple loop. In a bit we're
going to do both. So, this is both
a loop
and an
if test. And then we're going to do a couple
more that get a little bit more complicated.
Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
computer architecture for everybody. We're
playing with our 6504 emulator programming and
kind of working through some increasingly complex
samples as we go. So we're going to go into
the uppercase sample. Now the previous thing
we did was a loop and this is really more of
an if test. We're not this. We're not going
to do a loop in the next thing. We're going
to have an if test um and a uh a loop. So,
we're going to we're not going to store any data
here. We're going to just it's really simple.
We're just doing an if statement. We're going
to check in this one hard-coded variables. We're
going to check to see if P is greater than or
less than A. So, we're going to load accum into A,
the P letter, the constant P. We're going to
compare the constant A with the accumulator.
And if it is, and we're doing a a convert to
uppercase here. If it's already uppercase,
we're going to skip down. And if it's not
uppercase, we're going to convert it to
uppercase. And this will only work for lowercase
A through Z, but you get the idea. Okay? And so,
uh, so let's let's take a look here. Um, convert
to uppercase. So let's go ahead and so if we look
at these things, we got a load, we got our comp,
we got our immediate, so that's the letter P,
we got our compare, and then we have our
immediate, which is the letter A. And then we
have the branch if minus down to. And the branch
of minus is really skipping this subtraction and
going all the way to eight. So the if then else
that we've kind of got here is if it's minus,
we're going to skip down two instructions
to eight. If it is not minus, we're going
to run six and then that's going to be a subtract
immediate of 0x20. Hopefully you kind of see that
that's a two and that's a zero because the 0x20.
You can see those you at some point you should
start seeing the hex. Okay, let's go ahead and
just run this at full speed and maybe I'll talk a
little bit about it afterwards. I'm just going to
turn on narration and fire. Uh oh, no. I'm going
to step. I'm going to step. So, let's do the first
one. Let's load the letter P into the accumulator.
Load accumulator.
So that's a 0x70 which is lowercase P and ASKI.
Oh, hang on. Let me bring up the ASKI chart,
right? So now we can bring up the ASKI chart.
So that's kind of fun. So I got this little
ASKI chart for you. Quick computation. So 0x70
is a hopefully a lowercase P. Look at that. So
0x70 is a lowercase P. The assembler converted
this from a quote p quote which is one of its
many load accumulator uh syntaxes and it
chened it into 011 uh 011 0 0 and which
is the letter P. Now we're going to compare
this with the letter A. So where is that?
This is the we're instruction two now and we're
going to compare it with the A. And A is just
61 hex. And there it is. 61 hex. And so
let's just compare it. Run one instruction.
basically have it set so that P which was
in the accumulator is greater than A. So
we we're not we didn't set the zero flag and we
didn't set the negative flag. Okay? And if this
character that we just compared is less than
a then we're going to skip. If it's not we're
going to subtract 20 from it. So it's not going
to be very exciting. This is going to become
0x50 because we're going to subtract 0x20. So
let's go ahead and run that step. PC4 branch.
So the branch didn't get taken. It fell right
through into position 0x06. And now we're
going to do a subtract PC. Subtract with carry
immediate 0x20. So now the next instruction is
to stop. But you'll notice that we did subtract
that 70 from the the accumulator was 70 which
is the letter where were we the letter P and we
subtracted 20 hex to it which just happens to be
uppercase P. So this was a convert to uppercase
operation and the last step is just to stop PC08.
So we didn't store anything. We just are
showing a simple if then else which turns
into a sort of compare and skip based
on flag values. Okay. So, I hope you
found this particular useful uh in the in the
walkthrough and uh cheers and see you on the
Hello and welcome to another walkthrough for
computer architecture for everybody. We're
continuing on our CDC 6504 emulator. And now
we're going to load our most complex sample.
So let's
take a look at its assembly language. here
we have it. And let's move it over here. And
let's
move it up so we see all of the
instructions. There we go. We can just
barely see all the
instructions. This is our first thing that's
so long that we're going to end up in the
second
column of the instructions. So to start at
what we've got here, we got a data pseudo
operation
that fills the data memory with the string
hello E l with H being uppercase already and
E l. When
we're done, we want all these characters to
be upper uppercase. And so we're going to
write
a loop that's going to go through from zero
until it's and it's going to stop at a zero
bite and it's going to load the value, check
if it's already uppercase. If it's not, it's
going to subtract 20 to it, which we did
before because that's the mapping between
uppercase and
lowercase. And we're going to store it back
in. So we're done. 48 won't change because
that's already
uppercase. 65 will become 45. 65 6 C will
become 4C, etc. And then it'll stop and
it'll print out
the uppercase. So this is just a an
uppercase method in Python or whatever.
Okay. So
let's take a look at the code. We have a top
of a loop and we have a jump to the top of
the loop
at the bottom. This is a we're using x as
our iteration variable x because we have
this
really cool load that says I want to load
from zero offset by the current value in x.
Okay,
so x is going to start at zero because we're
going to clear it and then we're going to
add we're
going to slowly but surely add x. So this is
x= x + one each time through the loop. So
this
is the bottom of the loop, the continue area
where we're saying x++ or x= x+1 to advance
x through the string because we're going to
use x as the array offset as it's going
through our
little array. So we're going to load it.
We're going to load the value offset by x.
And then
we're going to immediately check to see if
we got a zero bite. And that's how we
terminate this loop
when we hit a zero bite. So we only want to
go through memory until we hit a zero bite.
Okay? So,
we don't want to run out of memory or blow
up or run into something else. We stop at a
zero
bite. And then we're going to check to see
if the letter we just got is already
uppercase. If it is,
that means it's less than lowercase a.
That's how ASKI works, right? So, let me go
ahead
and show you the ASI stuff. So if you look
at ASI you find that all the uppercase
characters
the lowercase characters are higher by a
factor of 20 hex. So a lowercase a is 61 and
uppercase
a is 41. You subtract 0x20 to get from
lowerase to upper. And our code is going to
upper. So,
we're checking to see if we are above or
below lowercase A. And if we're if
we're below lowerase I A already, we're
going to do a branch minus down here and
then increment to go to the next one. If on
the other hand, we are
above the letter A, then we're going to
subtract 20 and then we're going to store
that using our in index again as X. So x is
really cool. It's just going to be our
counter. And so this register is the
iteration variable. Well,
it is the iteration variable of our loop. So
let's go ahead and and get started. So
we'll turn on narration of execution. Line
ourselves up here. Take our first step.
Clear
the X register. PC0 X register. So now we're
at the top of the loop and we're going to do
a load from in memory location zero offset
by X register. So that the X register is
actually part
of this instruction. Okay. So let's go ahead
and load that PC01 accumulator from address
with X. Okay. So now you see that the
accumulator 0x48 and that is the uppercase
hello. And so the
next thing we're going to do and and that
load set the Z flag and the N flag and it's
neither
zero nor negative. And so let's go ahead and
run the if test to see if we're done with
the loop.
exit of the loop, but it didn't because
we're not we're not minus yet. And so that
was our that's
our top tested loop. And now what we're
going to do is we're gonna say if this is
greater than a if
it's if it's a or if it's less than a, we're
going to skip these next two lines. And the
next two
lines are a subtract of 0x20 and then an
indexed store into memory locations zero
offset by x. But
x is still position zero. So that is so this
is the letter H and it is already uppercase.
So we're
going to skip around this subtraction
calculation PC05 compare accumulator with
immediate 0x61
and now we're going to branch because it is
N. So
we're going to branch F minus. That means
we're already uppercase PCR
minus address. So it went to 0x0 D which
skipped around the subtraction. And now
we're at the
continue or the loop bottom the increment
part of the loop. And we're going to add one
to X
PC increment X register PC jump to address
one. Oh, I I I it went and did it
automatically. So,
we went up to the top of the loop and I
didn't catch it fast enough. So, it already
went and
X is now one. So, it's loading memory
location one into the accumulator. Okay. And
so the accumulator
now is nonzero. So we're we're going to
check to see if the loop is done. PC3 branch
equal address
0x10. And it didn't. So now we're going to
check to see the case of our current
character PC06.
So that is checking to see if it's above or
below a. and this one is above A and so
we're going to have to map it into
uppercase. So you'll notice that this this
BMI does not jump to
the c label. This one falls through PC 0x07
ifus address 0x0. So now we're at 0x09 not
0x0D. And
now we're going to do the subtract of 20 and
then we're going to store it into the
memory.
PC0x09 subtract with carry immediate 0x20
and now we're going to store it PC0 store
accumulator to address zero and X so so now
in location one we took this 45 that was our
calculated uppercase character and now it
has been stored in position one and so the
next
thing we do is add one and and jump to the
top of the loop. PC 0 increment x register
PC jump
to address one. So now we're at the top of
the loop. We're going to grab the next
instru the
next character because x is now two. So
we're going to grab this the the two offset
from our
array. PC01 load accumulator from address.
So we got 60. So, I'm going to just run this
a bit,
okay? And I'll try to stop it so that I can
show you the last iteration of the loop. So,
we'll watch X I'll probably try to catch it
while X sub the fourth iteration the
well the fifth iteration but sub4 is
running. Let's see if I can start it and
then catch it.
PC0x03 branch if equal address 0x10 PC 0x05
compare accumulator with immediate 0x61 PC
0x07
branch if minus address 0x0 we're on a
series of things that have to be converted
to uppercase
now PC store accumulator to address zero
index with X PC 0x0 D increment X register
PC0 X0 E jump
to address one PC 0x01 Load the accumulator
from address 0 and X with X PC 0x03 branch
if equal
address 0x10 PC 0x05 compare a cumulator
with immediate 0x61 PC 0x07 7 branch if
minus address
0x0 B PC 0x09 subtract with carry immediate
0x20 PC 0x0 B store accumulator to address
zero
index with X PC 0x0 D increment X register
PC0 X0E jump to address one PC 0x01 Lation
X PC 0x03 branch if equal address 0x10 PC
0x05 compare a cumulator with immediate 0x61
PC 0x07
branch if minus address 0x0 PC 0x0 Okay, so
I stopped it. So where are we at here?
We're about to store this last character. We
got it subtracted. So it's it's now
uppercase
and we're about to store it into position
offset by X and X. Our inoc our iteration
variable is four PC store accumulator to
address Z and X with X. The next thing we're
going to do
is increment X and so X is going to become
five. PC0X0 D increment X register. And now
we're going to jump to the top of the loop.
PC0 X0 E jump to address one. So now we're
at
the top of the loop. So X is five and we're
going to load the character at offset five.
And so now you'll notice as soon as we do
this accumulator is going to be zero and the
Z flag
is going to be set. PC0x01 load accumulator
from address z. So C got accumulator of zero
and we got Z. So now we will do a BEQ to
done. So we're going to jump right out of
this loop because now we've hit the zero
bite in our character array. PC03 branch if
address 0x10.
One more. PC0 break printed output. Hello.
So, it finished. It finished. And look,
it printed out an uppercase version of the
word hello. So, I recommend that you go in
and you
play with this and you load this and you
control the reset, the narrate, the
stepping. You
see how I'm doing it. , it it I'll tell you,
I I know what I'm doing and it's really hard
to
read these things and that's why I think of
this from an assembly language perspective.
trying to figure out. It doesn't hurt to
hover over and say, "Oh, that's the compare
instruction and that is the letter A." And
you can hover over these things and learn
some
stuff about what each of the locations is.
But so this is a nice little bit of code
that is a
loop with an if test. It's got increments.
It's got a continue in it. And so it is,
, a non-trivial piece of code. the the
smallest non-trivial piece of code that
I could fit into this particular emulator on
a screen that's small enough that maybe
that you can see this on a mobile device.
So, I hope you found this useful. Cheers.